# **Jorge Ignacio Lara Ceballos**

-Bachelor of Science in Aerial and Aerospace Systems

- -AWS Certified Solution Architect
- -Data Scientist Professional IBM

jorgelaraceballos@gmail.com https://www.linkedin.com/in/jorge-ignacio-lara-ceballos/ https://github.com/ddrrakkenn

Data Scientist with more than 6 years of experience, specialized in Python and R, and skills in libraries such as Pandas, Numpy and Scikit-learn, Matplotlib and Seaborn among others as well as neural networks. Experience in AWS as a teacher of cloud tools and customer segmentation projects in a US fintech and AB-InBev. Certified in project management by PMI, with experience in the aeronautical sector. Passionate about applying Data Science in various fields and industries. Currently as a Data Analyst course leader and responsible for its architecture and implementation.

## **EXPERIENCE**

Adalab, Lead Data Analyst— March 2024 - Today.

- I started as an instructor and within 3 months I was appointed as course leader in the Data Analyst area.
- Responsible for updating and improving Data Analyst educational content to make it relevant and aligned with current best practices and trends.
- Integrated Data course architecture planning (from content to methodologies).
- Implementation of Agile methodologies to track new assignments.

Technical advice regarding implementation of new technologies in the cloud (AWS).

**Stack**: Python, AWS Services, MySQL, Github, Seaborn, Pandas, Maltploilb, Numpy, Tableau, Powerbi Slack, Airtable

## Arkho.io, Sr Data Scientist— February, 2023- December 2023.

- Working with time series on AWS as Principal cloud service.
- Construction of achitecture for machine learning solutions.
- Implementation of Agile methodologies for control and monitoring of the company's projects.
- Improving the data governance of the contracting companies

**Stack**: Python, AWS Forecast, AWS S3, AWS Transcribe, AWS Lambda, AWS Cloudformation, AWS Comprehend, AWS Sagemaker, AWS Glue, AWS Quicksight, AWS Redshift, Jira.

## Pi Data Strategy & Consulting, Data Scientist—September, 2019 – February, 2023

- Creation of projects related to the banking sector such as RFM, Portfolio Aging and Propensity to Finance. In addition to an end to end system for customer sentiment analysis and call center activity monitoring.
- Multidisciplinary team leadership to improve the scope of projects in various business sectors.
- Implementation of Agile methodologies for control and monitoring of the company's projects.
- Improving the data governance of the contracting companies

**Stack**: Python, Pyspark, Databricks, Snowflake, Ovaledge, Excel, Azure, Jira, Microsoft 365, SQL, AWS S3, AWS Redshift.

## aB-InBev, Data Scientist - Segmentation Team — May, 2018 - September, 2019

- Optimized in 70% the scripts that already had given a more practical and easy to understand approach for the various data science teams of the company.
- Advised and implemented changes in the different scripts that the company had to perform segmentation tasks to increase the scope of the results.
- Implemented database enrichment with Google API for geolocation, which improved previous results

**Stack**: Python, Pandas, Numpy, Scikit-Learn, Geopy, Excel, Azure, Power BI, Google API Nearby search, SQL.

## **Jorge Ignacio Lara Ceballos**

-Bachelor of Science in Aerial and Aerospace Systems

- -AWS Certified Solution Architect
- -Data Scientist Professional IBM

jorgelaraceballos@gmail.com https://www.linkedin.com/in/jorge-ignacio-lara-ceballos/ https://github.com/ddrrakkenn

Quash.ai, Data Scientist — February, 2018 - June, 2018

- Improved by 80% the use of methodologies for using libraries for machine learning by implementing H20 as a hyperparameter tuning library.
- Developed new ways of working with big data through Dask and Modin.
- I was in charge of researching new implementations in the use of libraries (Dask, Modin) for handling big data in local environments without having to use cloud services.

Stack: Python, R, Pandas, Numpy, H20, Dask, Modin, Excel, Power Bi, Google data studio, Trello.

## Coderhouse, Data Scientist - Specialist — September, 2021 - Today.

- I contributed to the improvement of the student-teacher relationship in Data Science classes.
- I corrected work done by students and personally guided them in the understanding of the different Data Science tools (programming, statistical mathematics, problem solving methods).
- Contributed to the training of more than 200 students in various topics in data science, through classes in programming languages, statistics, machine learning among others, with a close and friendly approach for non-computer scientists.

**Stack**: Python, Pandas, Numpy, Excel, scikit-learn, Seaborn, Machine learning, supervised and unsupervised learning, AWS Services (for students).

## **SKILLS**

Programming Languages: <u>Advanced</u>: Python, R; <u>Intermediate</u>: Javascript.

Frameworks Tools: Advanced: Pandas, Numpy, Scikit-Learn, Matplotlib; Intermediate: Geopy, H2O,

Seaborn, Google API Nearby Search, Power BI, Tableau, Pyspark.

Data Base: Advanced: Microsoft SQL server, T-SQL; Intermediate: MongoDB, Maria DB, MySql.

Tools: Git, Slack, Discord, Jira, Microsoft Teams, Microsoft tools (Excel, Power point, Word, Access, MS Project), AWS Services (S3, EC2, Lambda, SQS, SNS, Cloudwatch, Cloudformation, Forecast, Transcribe, Comprehend, Sagemaker, Quicksight, Redshift, etc).

Agile: Project management, Scrum, Agile, Kanban.

Languages: Fluent: English; Intermediate: French; Native: Spanish.

### **EDUCATION**

Instituto Universitario Aeronáutico – Córdoba, Argentina. Bachelor in Aerospace Systems, December 2008. Universidad Tecnológica Nacional – Buenos Aires, Argentina. Postgraduate in Project Management, January 2019.

Coursera IBM- Córdoba, Argentina. Data Science Professional, August 2020.

Universidad Tecnológica Nacional – Buenos Aires, Argentina. Professional full stack developer, April 2021.

### **CERTIFICATIONS**

Certified Associate Project Management CAPM – PMI (Project Management Institute). 2020.

Data Science Methodology - Cognitive class. 2020.

Data Science Hands-On with Open Source Tools - Cognitive class. 2020.

Certified Database Administrator - Fundacion Carlos Slim. 2020.

Certified Big Data Visualizer – Fundación Carlos Slim. 2020.

Data Analyst Certification – Fundación Carlos Slim. 2020.

Project management with Agile methodologies and Lean approach – Fundación Telefónica Movistar. 2021.

Professional Certificate CEFR B2 Upper Intermediate - EnglishScore. 2021

Machine learning with Python - Advanced level - Coursera. 2022.

AWS Certified Cloud Practitioner - AWS (Amazon Web Services). 2023.

AWS Certified Solution Architect - Associate - AWS (Amazon Web Services). 2024.